howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com
that's Jim ruts show com today's guest
is Dan Schrag dan is the Sturgis Hooper
professor of geology at Harvard
University professor of environmental
science and engineering and director of
the Harvard University Center for the
environment as well as external faculty
at the Santa Fe Institute hi Jim great
to be here hey great to have you here
Dan this is the third episode in our
series on climate science and responding
to climate change let's start with how
did a geologist get interested in
climate change well as a geologist I'm
actually a geochemist my interest really
came through trying to reconstruct
ancient environments a big part of my
work involves studying earth history I'm
interested in how the environment has
changed over time over billions of years
over millions of years over thousands of
years and that includes the record of
climate change in earth history and in
some ways our understanding of the
future of climate change rests heavily
on our understanding of natural climate
variability in the past the earth has
experienced huge climate changes over
various time scales but this is nothing
like what we've experienced in the past
but it still frames our understanding
and helps us constrain the range of
possible outcomes
yeah and as I understand it the range is
really huge going back to the snowball
earth does that still a live hypothesis
that at one point the earth was almost
entirely covered with ice
absolutely and there are even lessons
from the snowball earth for our future
as well no there have been extreme
climate changes over Earth history and I
think for me they've helped me
appreciate the
what I think of as the timescales of
climate change and that's I think an
interesting part of it starting about
twenty years ago I was mostly working on
Paleo climate but I would give talks on
climate change and I would give a talk
about the history of climate you know
you probably saw me give a talk like
that in Santa Fe many years ago and and
would end you know and maybe in the last
minute or two of the talk would I'm wave
about what we should do about it
and I think I began personally they'd be
very frustrated with that that I wasn't
happy giving a talk about a huge problem
that was a planetary crisis but didn't
have much to say about what what we
should do about it and so I actually
started systematically thinking and
studying and working on devoting a part
of my research effort to thinking about
energy technology and then eventually
energy policy as well and so that's
become a big part of my portfolio as
well
cool yeah I've heard you talk on the
topic multiple times it s if I actually
attended the first s fi climate summer
school where you talk dad as I recall oh
wow that's the long time ago I think
yeah it really was
I remember the crowd trying to hush me
when I started asking questions about
geoengineering as if that was a bad
thing to talk about but we'll talk about
geoengineering oh I hope we'll talk
about it's a very important thing to
talk about exactly I was into
geoengineering when Indira engineering
wasn't cool so one of the things about
the history that has caught my attention
is I've read a paper
I don't not too long ago about some time
and they're not really deep ancient
paths I believe it was when we were
coming out of one of the Ice Ages or one
of the fluctuations around Ice Age there
was a very rapid increase in atmospheric
temperature approximately 15 C degrees
in 50 years is that a fact or fiction
would you say so I I think it's a it's a
fact out of context and let me explain
what was happening so one of the
surprises one of the lessons that we
learned from the Paleo climate record
climate at least locally doesn't always
change
slowly there could be what are called
abrupt changes that being said the exact
best examples of abrupt changes are not
really global or at least they may have
some larger than regional impacts but
they're not but but to say that the
whole world warmed by 15 degrees is a
gross misstatement but where this comes
from is the ice core records from
Greenland they're very interesting ice
core records from Greenland are very
different from Antarctica
partly because Greenland is really not a
polar glacier it's it's a more temperate
glacier it's high latitude but it's not
sitting up at the pole and during the
last ice age between 20,000 years ago
and say about 70 or 80 thousand years
ago
Greenland shows some very interesting
and very large temperature changes where
there were abrupt warming and as you
said it's it's between 10 and 20 degrees
Celsius of warming and it happened in
some cases extremely fast not faster
than 50 years and probably in just a few
years so this is extraordinarily fast
warming 10 or 20 degrees Celsius in just
a few years and then temperatures would
slowly cool down and then a very
abruptly cool down again in just a few
years they would return to their very
cold state they were in during the last
ice age so those are called dance guard
occurring events named after two
scandinavian scientists hans oscar and
willie dance guard who are poor pioneers
in the ice core field and helped to sort
of discover these cycles the mistake
that people have made is that they've
therefore assumed that the greenland ice
core implies that the whole northern
hemisphere was changing by that much and
it turns out that's really the mistake
so what you're saying is exactly correct
records from greenland do show and there
was a big one that happened about 15,000
years ago during the d glaciation but
these very abrupt warming's happened but
they really appear to be very local in
scope that is they had a hue
temperature change on the top of the
Greenland ice sheet three kilometers
above the surface if you actually went
to Europe you would see them but they
would be much more subtle they might be
fractions of a degree or maybe one or
two degrees or something like that you
see right similar patterns in caves in
China that have to do with precipitation
patterns and changes in the jet stream
but again much more subtle they're not
huge temperature changes so this isn't a
global change we actually think it has
to do with the distribution of sea ice
and the very large amplifying effect of
the ice sheets and in fact what's
interesting is you don't see these kind
of variability when the ice sheets melt
and they go away so since about you know
10,000 years ago we don't see any
variability like that in fact the name
for the recent period the Holocene is
named because of its climate relative
stability so that's kind of interesting
that's very good context and we talked
about 1.5 to 2.5 degrees Celsius and I
go civilization will survive that might
be unpleasant but 15 degrees C and 10
years we'd be completely glad to
hear the bat seems unlikely yeah that's
not gonna happen but but you know it's
said at the same time don't
underestimate how big a change one and a
half degrees is why don't I have degrees
Celsius is a lot of temperature change
just to give some perspective on this
the difference in global temperature
between the glacial maximum 20,000 years
ago when we had an ice sheet covering
half of North America the ice came you
know where I'm sitting in Boston was
under a kilometer of ice down in New
York is where the glaciers ended you
know you had all of Canada being covered
by ice part of the northern US there was
so much ice on continents 20,000 years
ago that sea level was about a hundred
and thirty meters lower than today
that's how much water was taken out of
the ocean and put onto land in the form
of snow and ultimately ice so so that's
a big deal and the global temperature
change was about five degrees Celsius so
think about when you talk about one and
a half or two degrees warming you have
to calibrate people
five degrees is the difference between
the last glacial maximum 20,000 years
ago and today so two degrees is still a
really big deal and five degrees warmer
you know is is like a completely
different planet so if we go to five
it's very very very bad I guess that's
about where we get if we burned all the
coal it might even be worse than that
oh absolutely but I think I think it's
important to understand you know I've
been giving talks recently to public
audiences and climate change and and and
there's so many details and there's so
much complexity in climate science I've
tried to distill down what I've learned
over 25 years of thinking about this
problem and and I think there are two
essential elements that everybody needs
to understand and the rest is detail the
rest are fascinating details and we
could talk for hours about those details
but the two really important elements
are one that this is fundamentally a
collective action problem that is global
and humans are really bad at collective
action problems and when I say that I
mean that that this isn't about that
just China or the US and it really
requires global cooperation to fix the
problem you know doesn't mean that every
last person needs to be completely
fossil free but essentially world
society needs to stop using fossil fuels
and we need to stop increasing co2 in
the atmosphere the second part of the
problem is that every aspect of the
problem has long timescales and put
together those two components are killer
I'll talk more about what that means
these long timescales but I I mean the
timescale of the climate system the
oceans the ice sheets also the timescale
of the carbon cycle which is
unbelievably long and finally and this
is the part that a lot of people in the
technology world or in or you know who
think about innovation don't really
understand which is the time scale for
energies the energy system is also
unfortunately very long this isn't
something we can actually you know
change we can't turn on a dime that
quickly but I think that's really
fundamental because we're dealing with a
global collective action problem
the likes of which we've never really
dealt with before and coupled with
longtime skills and humans are really
bad at both of those things yep thank
you we'll get into a lot of those topics
as we go along but I like to
particularly call out collective action
problems one of the things I've
highlighted again and again in the whole
problem of how we build a social
operating system and the best book I've
ever read on the collective action
problem is by Mansur Olson it's a book
called the logic of collective action
and that encouraged our listeners to go
read that book they want to know more
about how hard it is for groups of
people to actually get together and do
the right thing let's move on to a
little bit more detail in discussions of
climate change we hear a lot about
climate models ensembles of climate
models you know I've seen these graphs
with all the whole series of climate
models laid over each other how relevant
are they what do they tell us what do
they not tell us well
climate models are very important tools
for those of us studying the climate
system both in terms of trying to
understand mechanisms and also thinking
about forecasts for the future but I
think it's really important to
understand that we're doing an
experiment on the planet that hasn't
been done ever in geologic history there
are some analogs the best natural
analogue we might talk about is about 55
million years ago but it's it's a decent
analogue but it's not a perfect analogue
because it happened on a much longer
time scale so the truth is that we
really don't know a lot of things about
the Earth's system and how it's going to
respond to the kind of changes we've
made to the atmosphere and so models are
really important because the system is
too complicated to just you know do a
calculation on on a blackboard and or a
piece of paper and and predict exactly
what's gonna happen
at the same time we have to always
maintain a sense of skepticism and
questions about the models because there
are parts of the system we don't
understand that is you know they
represent the best understanding of the
earth system but we're taking the earth
system outside of any realm of
experience and therefore
the history of observations is only
limited in its ability to predict the
future does that make sense absolutely
and you know we both tend to think in
terms of complex systems and we do know
that the ability to predict complex
systems out of ways under major
perturbation is relatively limited best
we can do is build various models and
maybe some sense we can't call our shots
yeah although although again I think
what's important for people to
understand is that for the basic physics
of this it's not that complex a system
the basic physics of the greenhouse
effect and the basic physics of how the
system worked was known more than a
hundred years ago John Tyndall you know
understood the basic physics of the
greenhouse effect he did these elaborate
experiments showing how carbon dioxide
would absorb infrared radiation and
svante arrhenius basically you know he
for those who you don't know who he was
he was the first Nobel Prize winner in
chemistry from Sweden he was the first
Nobel Prize with laureate from Sweden
he's considered one of the founders of
physical chemistry and in the you know
around 1903 1905 he was already writing
about the greenhouse effect and he
actually suggested that we would
probably double carbon dioxide levels
because of burning coal and that and
that he calculated the effect would be
about 4 degrees Celsius so the basic
physics of the system was understood
more than a hundred years ago this is
not new science it's not unbelievably
complex yes the earth is a complex
system and most of what we don't know
are things that could hurt us but but
the basic physics of how the earth warms
is actually pretty understandable with
relatively simple models that are not
that complex and what I mean by that
really is you know the basic idea of the
radiative equilibrium so when you
increase greenhouse gases in the
atmosphere we understand again going
back to John Tyndall and spontaneous 100
years ago we know that the Earth's gonna
warm up and that's just because we've
increased essentially the absorption of
infrared coming off the surface
essentially we've increased the boundary
layer you could think of it as putting a
thermal blanket on the earth and
result the surface temperatures gonna
heat up until the outgoing radiation
balances the incoming solar radiation
that's very simple what's more
complicated if the earth were completely
covered with land climate change would
be so much simpler because essentially
it would very quickly warm up and would
achieve that radiative equilibrium and
we'd be all set
but the fact that the ocean is in fact
that 70% of your surface is covered with
water makes the earth much more
interesting and complicated and the
reason is that the ocean is this huge
heat sink
it's a giant tub of cold water think
about what would happen you know in your
bedroom if you had a giant bathtub that
covered 70% of your bedroom and was a
big ice tub filled with ice water and
now you turn up the thermostat so you
can sleep there 270 degrees or 68
degrees or whatever and what you
discover is it's still really cold in
your room for a very long time and
that's because the heat is going into
warming the ice and and there's heat
exchange and the ice bath is cooling the
room and you have to wait for that ice
bath to warm up before that you reach an
equilibrium temperature the same things
happening with the earth so the ocean is
absorbing heat and mixing it down and if
you actually look at the pattern of
warming the spatial pattern of warming
you see that the continents have warmed
about twice as much on average as the
oceans and that's because the oceans are
actively sucking up heat and that's both
good news and bad news the good news is
we haven't really had to experience the
full impact of our of our changes in the
atmosphere that we've made the bad news
is that we're committed to probably at
least 50% more and maybe more than that
maybe you know maybe 70% additional
warming that we've already experienced
is still to come into the future so if
we stopped burning fossil fuels tomorrow
the earth is going to keep warming for
centuries maybe even millennia that's a
little that's a little scary
could you explain that I know it it's
true and I have gone through the math
myself but
if you could explain how that thermal
inertia works and it's plain that
languages you could well I think it's
exactly the same as the example I gave
with the bathtub in your bedroom
essentially the oceans are a giant heat
sink so when you increase greenhouse
gasses in the atmosphere the earth wants
to achieve a certain temperature that
will achieve what's called radiative
equilibrium that's when outgoing
infrared radiation that is heat that
goes out to space is equivalent to the
amount of energy coming in from solar
radiation so when you add greenhouse
gases you create an imbalance you absorb
more of the infrared radiation and
therefore the surface temperature has to
rise to achieve a new equilibrium so
that you're in balance again what comes
in has to go out ninety percent of the
imbalance today is actually goes into
warming the oceans a few percent goes
into warming the surface a few percent
goes into warming the two melting ice
but but 90% of the energy imbalance
because of the greenhouse gases we've
added in the atmosphere goes into
heating the ocean so if you sort of say
what is global warming the answer is
global warming is really ocean warming
that's where most of the energy is
actually going and the time scale of
mixing of the oceans you know mixing all
that cold water up and eventually
warming the whole ocean or at least the
whole upper half of the ocean the time
scales thousands of years and so until
the ocean is in equilibrium with this
new atmosphere essentially it's gonna
keep absorbing heat and keep warming and
that's gonna take more than a thousand
years
so we've already committed the earth to
substantial additional warming that we
haven't yet experienced does that make
sense
absolutely I'll play it back in as plain
English as I can for our audience
the ocean is storing energy and the
result of that as it mixes thoroughly is
that the average temperature the upper
layers of the ocean will gradually rise
and then that warmer water sitting next
to the atmosphere will slowly raise the
temperature of the atmosphere that's
right so so for example 20,000 years ago
when the earth was about four or five
degrees colder
the deep ocean was about four degrees
colder as well the deep ocean was very
close to the freezing point of seawater
which is about minus two degrees because
of salt it's it's below zero Celsius so
you know the ocean was much colder
20,000 years ago and you could think of
the fact that the ocean was sort of more
in equilibrium with a colder climate by
the way carbon dioxide levels were about
a hundred and eighty parts per million
back then that was one of the reasons
why the earth was so cold so in the last
10,000 years carbon dioxide has been
between 260 and 280 parts per million
and the atmosphere and ocean have
equilibrate it to the point where the
ocean is you know about one or two
degrees in the deep ocean in the
Atlantic it's a little warmer it's about
3 or 4 degrees because it's a little
saltier but but essentially that is in
equilibrium with the modern atmosphere
or with the with a pre-industrial
atmosphere now that we have added
greenhouse gases the oceans are slowly
warming and probably they will warm you
know another three or four degrees and
we've just started the heat uptake from
the ocean is is happening steadily and
slowly and in fact it is one of the
major reasons why sea level is rising
certainly ice melting is contributing to
sea level rise but one of the major
reasons for sea level rise is just
thermal expansion of seawater that is
ocean warming very good very well stated
I think that will help our audience
understand how important this ocean
warming phenomena is both with respect
to its long term inertial effects and
this is very important people to know
most though of the sea level rise we've
seen so far is just as Dan said the
water gets bigger when you heat it up
another issue about the ocean which we
hear talked about a lot is acidification
of the ocean what's your take on that so
I actually think acidification first of
all people have to understand the actual
change in pH of the ocean is actually
pretty subtle first of all the ocean is
slightly basic the pH of seawater is
about 8.2 or 8.3 the deep ocean it's a
little bit less than that because of the
biological pump that actually takes
biological productivity
algae bacteria Falls to the deep ocean
it gets respired by so plankton they eat
it and turn it back into carbon dioxide
which slightly acidifies the deep ocean
so the deep ocean is a little little
lower pH than the surface ocean but both
are more basic than neutral right so
they are both well above 7 ocean
acidification really has to do with the
timescale of the carbon cycle we're
adding carbon dioxide to the atmosphere
more quickly than the ocean can absorb
it and the reason is because the ocean
only mixes so fast if we could mix the
oceans instantly if we had a giant
mixing rod that would mix the oceans
very quickly 80 to 90 percent of the
carbon dioxide we've added to the
atmosphere would go into the ocean so in
the long run you could say that the
solution or at least 80 to 90% of the
solution to pollution is solution that
is the oceans gonna take care of our
problem the difficulty is the time scale
for that ocean uptake is probably
several thousand years and so 80% of the
co2 is likely to go away but only over
the next next several thousand years and
therefore we have to still live in the
next few centuries and so we've got a
problem because of that disequilibrium
because co2 is going higher in the
atmosphere and the ocean isn't taking it
up fast enough the surface ocean which
mixes and equilibrates with this
atmosphere relatively quickly that is
the upper 100 or 200 meters of the ocean
is actually seeing higher levels of
carbon dioxide and it's pH is dropping a
little bit like a tenth or two tenths of
a pH unit so it turns out that's
actually a pretty subtle effect what it
tends to do is make it slightly more
difficult for organisms that make their
shells out of calcium carbonate and
we're talking about corals
we're talking about clams and other
mollusks we're talking about algae
called Kaka Litha fors they grow their
shells out of calcium carbonate that
then fall on the ocean floor and form
limestone or chalk and this the slight
change in pH of seawater can affect the
ecology of those organisms
now it sounds very scary and some people
say oh oh should acidification it makes
it sound like the whole ocean is gonna
turn into acid and everything's gonna
die that is really not true in fact I
would say that the total effects of
ocean acidification on the ecology of
the ocean right now are still mostly
unknown I don't even know in what
direction they're gonna go certainly
they're gonna probably hurt coral reefs
and favor organisms that don't grow
their shells out of calcium carbonate
but I would say this first of all by far
the biggest impact on the ecology of the
oceans that we've experienced so far is
overfishing you know we have basically
ruined the marine ecosystem just by
taking so many fish out of the ocean and
so ocean acidification is sort of low on
the list of major concerns relative to
overfishing the second point is that the
warming itself that is climate change
itself and the warming of the surface
ocean is profoundly changing the ocean
ecosystem and that probably is going to
have a much bigger effect on ocean
ecology than the acidification so it's
not that ocean acidification is a
non-issue
I just think it's really a minor issue
relative to warming of seawater and also
the impact of overfishing
we've just devastated when overfishing
includes by the way the trawling of the
oceans you know that most of the of the
continental shelf that is the shallower
parts of the oceans
we've just dragged sleds over it and
just completely destroyed it like like
dragging a heavy rake over you know it
essentially looks like pavement now
instead of a natural ecosystem it's just
horrible well thanks for putting all
that into perspective I think that's
very useful what about the data how good
is our data about the actual levels of
climate increase and how does the data
that's been collected and clean compared
to what we've seen in the models so I
would say that in general our observing
system of the earth is I would say it's
a half-empty half-full kind of problem
the answer is there are some great
successes especially
recently there are also some places
where we could do a lot better
there are certainly parts of our Earth
observing system we'd love to have more
carefully calibrated data one of the
challenges with certain types of climate
data is that it could be spatially
variable so think of the problem of
recording precipitation you know we know
this from Santa Fe you know you can be
in New Mexico and there can be rain in
one place and no rain and you know three
miles away it's highly spatially
variable so actually recording average
precipitation rates is actually pretty
complicated and if you want to do it
globally including in places where they
don't necessarily have the same
infrastructure that we have in the US it
gets really complicated so for example
most of the studies of what the impact
of climate change on agriculture is
going to be is from the US because
that's where the good data are or maybe
sometimes from the U we really don't
have very good data from Africa or
certain parts of Siberia or Latin
America and that's and that's partly
just because the quality of the
observations is too low the satellite
era has helped in some respects but in
some cases there really is no substitute
for good ground-based observations
another problem with climate change is
that observing systems change over time
a classic example of this is
measurements of ocean temperature there
are scientists who still argue over
correcting you know back in the day
there used to be buckets that people
would use on ships they would use cloth
bags to take seawater and then measure
the temperature and merchant ships would
actually do this and then they used to
switch from cloth buckets to metal
buckets or wooden buckets and then you
actually switch today most ocean
measurements are made on merchant ships
using an engine intake system and it
turns out that every time you change the
measurement system they're actually some
systematic and subtle changes in the
temperature that you measure and
have to correct for these errors and the
problem with climate change is you need
absolute calibration with very high
precision and that's a very big problem
so when you change the measurement
system you kind of have to think about
the calibration problem and that's
always been a problem for earth
observations let's talk about some of
the good news though the good news is
that you know 20 years ago most of our
observations say of the ocean warming
which is we said is you know that is
global warming is ocean warming ninety
percent of the energy is going into the
warming the ocean most of that
information in fact all of it really
came from a bunch of cruises where
oceanographers would go out and tow a
wire drop a wire over the side with a
thermometer and basically measure the
temperature with depth and then come up
and you know and and they would do a
transect at some point in the year and
then some other crews would go out and
do another one and that's how we knew
about the ocean so it was kind of kind
of awful there was a great quote from
Hanks Tom Hanks Tama was a famous
physical oceanographer he was at Harvard
and MIT and mostly at Woods Hole Hanks
Tamil he remarked that the determination
of climatological conditions in the
atmosphere by means analogous to those
used by oceanographers would be to use
half a dozen automobiles and kites to
which air sounding instruments were
attached and by doing all of their work
on dark moonless nights when they
couldn't see what was happening in their
medium so for the history of
Oceanography that's how oceanographers
studied the oceans they went out on
ships and they dropped wires and
measured what was down there they
couldn't see and you know they would go
out randomly on ships and measure and so
they're parts of the ocean that just
weren't measured and you certainly
didn't have long time series starting in
the 80s we had a few places where we
would actually install moorings and get
continuous measurements but they were
just a handful of spots around the
oceans and and not and not an only
shallow not very deep so you know we
really didn't understand the oceans and
to a great
in terms of our observing system all of
that changed in the 2000s we created a
system and it's really something that
hasn't gotten enough attention is called
Argo AR geo and these are floats
these are floats that actually sit down
at about a thousand meters in the ocean
and they sit there they're not driven
they're just they randomly drift but a
thousand meters the currents aren't very
strong so they sit there for nine days
and then on the tenth day they slowly
drop down to about 2,000 meters and then
they slowly rise up to the surface and
record the temperature and the salinity
every 10 centimeters and that takes
about six hours and when they get to the
surface they beam the data back down
back to a back to a satellite and then
they sink back down to a thousand meters
and sit there again for nine days and
these are automated floats that have a
lifetime of about five or six years and
it's kind of incredible there are
currently something like 4,000 floats
out there around the world oceans and
what's amazing is there's something like
30 nations that have all contributed to
this program this is an international
partnership for earth observations that
has been extraordinarily successful so
in in just a few years we had collected
more data on the temperature and
salinity of the ocean then in the
previous hundred years of Oceanography
that's how it's a revolution in Earth
observing systems where that sounds
really interesting it's amazing and so
we have data now over the last about 15
years for and we can actually measure
the ocean warming so now it's not a
speculation whether the ocean is warming
we measure ocean warming and if you sort
of say do we know if global warming is
happening the answer is yes because if
we can measure ocean warming that's
where 90% of the energy is going that
absolutely proves what's actually going
on in terms of the radiative imbalance
and I think that's really fundamentally
important so that's a great success of
Earth observations in terms of the
models the answer is the models are good
but not perfect there's
a lot of details of the real world that
they don't have some of which I think
are important for a sort of intermediate
time scale forecasts I'll give you an
example one of the things the model
climate models don't do very well is
they don't actually simulate the kind of
decade to decade variability that we see
in the real system and many of us think
that the reason for that is that the
resolution of the models just isn't good
enough they're not actually simulating
the mixing the eddies the complexity of
the turbulent flow in the oceans because
they're the grid spacing is just too big
and so it smears it all out and so the
result of that is they don't have some
of the physics in it that we actually
that produce some of the decade to
decade variability and therefore that
limits their skill in predicting the
future at least on intermediate
timescales that doesn't mean they're
wrong altogether it means that you know
if you say how well our climate
forecasts of you know what the
temperature's going to be in 2040 or
2050 the answer is there's a fair amount
of uncertainty because of the decade a
decade variability that we see in the
real system and we know the models don't
do that very well that being said if you
go further out they actually probably
have more skill because the overall
temperature rise is greater and I think
the most important thing to understand
is the biggest uncertainty in all of
this is actually what humans are gonna
do you know we don't know how much
greenhouse gas we're gonna put into the
atmosphere over the next hundred years
and so by far the biggest uncertainty in
climate forecasts is actually the human
part of the system we'll get to that
later but yeah thankfully now the bottom
line does the last 15 years of this
system was an Argo did you say it was
Argo yeah what does it show about the
data the last 15 years well it shows
that the earth is that the oceans are
warming and it's warming at about the
rate that people are predicting the
error bars will continue to go down as
we get longer time series so right now
we only have you know about 15 years
we'd like to have more but you know in
general it's mostly consistent with the
models and the models are slowly
converging
you know it used to be that there was a
big argument among climate models this
goes back to the early 80s the early
days of climate models in the 70s and
80s in the u.s. there were two main
groups one was a gist net which is a
NASA lab in New York and the other was a
GFDL which is at Princeton New Jersey
and a NOAA lab national ocean atmosphere
administration and there was the NOAA
work was pioneered by a scientist named
Sookie Manabi great climate scientist
who pioneered development of climate
models and the work at guess was led by
a guy named Jim Hanson who is one of the
heroes and climate change gave a famous
testimony to the Senate in 1988 that
changed a lot of people's thinking about
climate change anyway Jim Hansen's model
and Souki manami's model they both did
runs with doubling of carbon dioxide and
they got different answers I think Sukie
minami's model got two degrees Celsius
and Jim Hansen's model got four degrees
Celsius I think that's right I could
have gotten it backwards but I think I'm
pretty sure that's the right order it
doesn't really matter
one got two degrees the other got four
degrees and so a famous scientist at MIT
named Jules Charney said that the
climate sensitivity which we just
thought defined as how the earth
responds to a doubling of carbon dioxide
levels was about 3 plus or minus one and
a half degrees you know there was he
just split the two numbers and said okay
the number is three because you got two
one one group got to the other got four
so the right number is three obviously
that sounds a little arbitrary and there
was a big discussion about is it one or
two degrees or is it three or four
degrees and the answer matters right if
if if doubling of carbon dioxide level
which seems inevitable soon after a
mid-century for the earth well
guaranteed to get there the question is
how much higher will go in terms of
carbon dioxide levels but but doubling
of co2 if that actually produces three
to four degrees of warming instead of
one to two degrees of warming that's a
really big deal we need to understand
that
and what was interesting was most of the
climate models when they were compared
against recent data over the 20th
century suggested that the number was
small was probably closer to two degrees
and the interesting than was those of us
those of us who studied the Paleo
climate system the last ice age
were the ancient climates of the Eocene
fifty million years ago we realized that
in fact if it was only two degrees per
doubling of co2 you actually couldn't
explain the changes in climate we'd seen
in the geologic past we had a pretty
good idea of how much carbon dioxide
levels changed and you couldn't explain
that with just two degrees per doubling
of co2 you needed something more like
four degrees and so there was this
argument about was it two degrees or was
it four degrees most of that has gone
away and here's the simple resolution
and again has to do with time scale it's
really interesting the time scale of
warming and the time scale of the oceans
the models when they compare to 20th
century data they're looking at the
short time scale they're looking at the
immediate response of the earth system
and again if a substantial fraction of
the warming is not yet happened because
of ocean warming and the timescale of
ocean mixing that actually reconciles
the two perspectives so the climate
sensitivity of the models due to you
know a doubling of co2 on the short
timescale is probably closer to two
degrees Celsius per doubling but if you
wait for the oceans to warm
then it gets closer to three or four
degrees and that's where the how
everything is sort of come into
agreement I know that's a bit of a long
tangent but I think that's important to
understand yeah that's very important
just you know a lot of the conversation
I'm talking about policy focuses on like
2100 but it is important and it we
absolutely have to do something before
2100 and a lot but it's also important
to realize that we've pulled the
slingshot way back and it'll be
impacting 2,200 2,300 and 2,400
so hopefully we'll have techno fixes by
that point which we'll talk about here
in a minute well
I would I would I would caution you Jim
first of all the last thing you should
ever do and please don't ever do this
again is to call geoengineering a techno
fix because it's not it is absolutely
not a techno fix I would purge that word
from your vocabulary with regard to
climate change because there is no
techno fix the thing that people need to
understand is the timescale of the earth
systems is really long and this gets
into this question of human response we
see this all the time and I know you
don't want to talk about politics I'm
not going to talk about politics per se
but I will say that a lot of the
rhetoric from environmental groups and
from political candidates who want to do
something about climate change they
struggle with this because they know
that people who care about climate
change want them to fix it right away
and the problem with climate change is
it's a long time scale problem and it
can't be fixed overnight
you can't decarbonize the u.s. in ten
years and even if you could it wouldn't
solve the problem because it's a global
collective action problem and you can't
decarbonize the whole world in ten years
and even if you did that again the time
scale for the earth to keep warming is
still millennia and so you know you're
not gonna fix this problem quickly it
just is not possible and I think that's
really really important to understand
let me give you a perspective on this we
haven't talked about the ice sheets yet
but the ice sheets have anis terrifying
long time scale I think people maybe
understand a little bit intuitively how
big the ice sheets are but I want to
give people an example of just how large
they are so Greenland is the smaller of
the two polar ice sheets Greenland is
not really polar it's it's more
temperate Antarctica is much bigger
so if Greenland melted completely sea
level on average would rise about 7.2
meters right or about 23 feet that's
tiny compared to Antarctica which is 50
or 60 meters of sea level equivalent but
what I think people don't understand is
just how big that really is so you know
Greenland
so big it actually has its own tidal
force if people never heard this but
it's very interesting so let's imagine
you melted suppose we waved a magic wand
and we melted a seventh of Greenland
okay so you melt us at seventh of
Greenland and on average sea level rises
by one meter okay but that's a global
average it turns out that if you were
standing in the southern tip of
Greenland you would see sea level fall
about 19 meters that's interesting and
strange do you know why that is no tell
us that sounds very interesting it's
because of the gravitational pull of the
mass of the Greenland ice sheet that is
just like the moon pulling the water
around which is what causes the cycle of
tides that we're used to the Greenland
ice sheet it's so massive that it's
actually pulling seawater towards it so
when you lose a seventh of Greenland you
lose so much mass that the sea level
locally recedes because it's got reduced
gravitational attraction
even though on average sea levels rising
one meter it's falling by 19 meters
right next to Greenland is that
incredible that is wow that's a new
thing that's worth knowing but the
interesting part of that is if you think
we can actually physically control
something as big as the Greenland ice
sheet I think you should think again
this is a very big engineering challenge
and by the way Greenland is tiny
compared to Antarctica and and and
there's a big difference between the two
high sheets the cause of mass loss from
Greenland is mostly and the risk for the
future is mostly due to summer melting
so every summer Greenland melts on the
periphery sometimes in 2012 it melted
just about everywhere on Greenland but
but most years it only melts in the
perimeter of the ice sheet and then in
the winter more snow falls and the net
today is negative that is it's losing
mass
if contributing something like a little
more than half a millimeter a year close
to probably somewhere between 1/2 and 1
millimeter years something like point 8
millimeters per year based on data we
have from a satellite that measures the
gravitational field of the earth
so 0.8 millimeters per year that's not
that much right think about that that's
that's point 8 millimeters a year is
like 8 centimeters over a century that
doesn't sound so terrifying the problem
is we've seen very dramatic changes in
the last 10 or 20 years and so the
concern is this could dramatically
accelerate and the risk is much more
intense summer melting in Greenland and
Antarctica it's melting more slowly it's
less it's probably closer to a half a
millimeter a year of mass loss but
what's interesting about Antarctica is
the mechanism is different
most of Antarctica the potential is
different you know we heard a report
recently in the news that it was like 67
degrees fahrenheit in Antarctica for the
first time ever but that was in the
peninsula that was that was pretty far
away from the core of Antarctica most of
Antarctica is way below the freezing
point and therefore even in the middle
of the summer the Antarctic summer it's
still well below freezing and so it
could warm quite a bit and still not
melt and so some hot scientists actually
think Antarctica will gain mass sometime
this century because the snowfall will
increase and exceed the amount of ice
that gets lost at the edges but what's
scary about Antarctica is something else
the mechanism for mass loss from
Antarctica is not summer melting because
it's so cold it's actually the flow of
ice into the ocean and right now that
flow is being impeded by large pieces of
ice that are floating on the ocean
called ice shelves the recent Pine
Island Ice Shelf has been breaking up
and it was in the news recently you know
an enormous iceberg the size of Rhode
Island dropped off or something like
that but the big concern is that if we
lose the big ice shelves and the biggest
ones are called the Ross
shelf the Rani ice shelf those ice
shelves act a little bit like corks in a
bottle they actually keep the glaciers
sitting near the coast from flowing into
the ocean now the ice shelves themselves
don't change the level because they're
already floating on the ocean
they're already displacing seawater but
if they break off suddenly there could
be very rapid flow of ice from the land
into the ocean and that would affect the
sea level and a scary thing about that
is not the time scale they're they're
not it's not gonna happen overnight
because fundamentally glacial flow can
only happen so fast the scary part is
that that glacial flow doesn't care what
the surface temperature is it's really
driven by gravity these glaciers are
flowing downhill and once you lose the
barrier you lose the ice shelf there's
really not much we can do about it
you've now committed the earth to
probably centuries - maybe millennia of
continued sea-level rise you know maybe
10 or 20 meters of sea level rise for
the next millennia and there's and
future generations are just gonna have
to deal with it and so we've made
decisions now that affect the earth for
thousands of years and and we're not
thinking about it that way mmm that's an
interesting thought glad I live at 2200
feet not gonna be pretty for a whole lot
of the world's population that lives
within 10 meters of sea level and that's
what a billion people something like
that yeah although I got to tell you if
the time scale this is again one of the
fascinating parts of climate change
economists will tell you look over a
hundred years you can move cities part
of the problem of climate change you
know you know I've been watching what's
happening with coronavirus right now
around the world people stopping travel
quarantine eating people and thinking
about how people are reacting to
coronavirus versus reacting to climate
change think about how different that is
I think it's fascinating to see how
people deal with an acute situation and
they panic nobody is asking well what's
the cost-benefit of cutting off flight
stick to China right we're just doing it
it's a public health issue it's an
emergency
we're canceling flights we're shutting
down a Chinese cities literally people
are not allowed out of their homes in
China and by the way that may be the
right decision
I'm not questioning that decision I'm
just saying it's interesting how people
respond to an acute concern whereas the
long timescales change everything and
and here's what makes me uncomfortable
we're really not good at thinking about
the economics or the ethics of long
timescales you can convince yourself
that on a several hundred year timescale
economically it makes sense to do
nothing
let's see level rise and move people and
adapt to it because over a few hundred
years think about it none of the cities
we have in the world are more than 200
years old I mean obviously Paris London
or much older than that but most of
their buildings are much younger than
that you could rebuild them no problem
and yet I have the sense that 200 years
from now people are gonna you know our
descendants are gonna look back at us
with horror they're gonna say what were
they thinking yep look what they did to
us and yet at any step in the way it
seems logical and practical to do very
little and I think that's what's what's
very troubling about this long time
scale thing we really don't know how to
deal with long timescales and think
about the long term commitments you know
in economics you deal with discount
rates and there's a whole discussion of
what the right discount rate should be
but you know I think they've confused
something discount rates really asked
the question you know how much
rationally should you pay to avoid some
damage in the future
and they've quite reasonably recognised
that a dollar today is worth more than a
dollar 50 years from now and therefore
you should pay less to avoid something
that's gonna happen 50 years from now
than to avoid something that's gonna
happen tomorrow
and that's fine I think what's loft left
is the moral ethical dimension of this
which is we're talking about decisions
we're making for literally thousands of
generations of humans that haven't even
been born yet and so the question is not
how much should we pay or how much are
we willing to pay the question is what
moral obligation do we have to provide
future generations on this planet the
same kind of opportunities that we have
and that's a very different question yep
very well said and it's actually worse
than that Dan if we took the economic
discount rates we would still be taking
more action than let's say the United
States is taking today because we know
from cognitive science and behavioral
economics that your typical non
scientifically educated person tends to
discount things hyperbolically even more
extremely than the exponential that you
get from fixed interest rates and so our
politics is driven probably to a
significant degree by hyperbolic
discounting where the future disappears
entirely which is even worse hyperbolic
discounting can be it depends on what
the rate is
actually maybe a better thing for the
long term because what hyperbolic
discounting does is actually say the
long term future is not where zero
exponential of discounting the long term
future is literally zero
you know asymptotes to zero but with
hyperbolic discounting the distant
future is worth something it's just
worth very little and it's the same so
we don't distinguish between and that's
and that's behavioral the consistent
with experiments when you ask people how
much is it worth to you to to avoid
something 200 years from now or 500
years from now the answer is it's worth
something it's just very very little and
it doesn't really matter whether it's
two hundred or five hundred or a
thousand so that's where the hyperbolic
idea comes from and so that is a little
better than some ways then exponential
discounting but I think the whole
discussion is still misplaced because
that's not really what the question is
it's it's not how much should we be
willing to pay
it's a question of what moral obligation
do we have and that's a very different
way of framing the issue Murray gelt
Mike we you know Murray for sure and I
do too absolutely let e rest in peace
one of the great souls I've ever met his
strong proponent was that for
calculating long-term impact on humanity
like climate change that the only moral
answer was to use a zero discount rate
you know it's interesting I think just
the problem of the whole exponential
discounting framework might lead you to
that framework my friend part of the
descriptor who's a economist at
Cambridge University in England
Partha argues that for all we know the
discount rate the appropriate discount
rate is actually negative that is think
about it if the impacts of climate
change are really catastrophic and
actually erode the economy and result in
negative economic growth then the
rational thing is to use a negative
discount rate which is again that's very
controversial among economists but I
think it's an interesting question very
good the other side of your work is
analyzing studying energy technologies
and policy including carbon capture and
storage you know low carbon synthetic
fuels etc why don't we start with an
overview from your perspective on where
we are with our energy technologies and
which ones look like they ought to be
ready within the necessary planning
horizons to start to get us to his Net
Zero Carbon society in some reasonable
period i'm particularly interested but
mention all a big li interested in
carbon capture and storage so let's give
the dance rag view on where we are with
energy related technologies so i think
the answer is that because of interest
around the world including the US but
but not necessarily focused here there's
a lot of good news but the fundamental
fact about the time scale of
decarbonizing our global economy still
holds let's review some of the good news
really quickly so if you think about 10
or 11 years ago when Obama first came
into office in 2009 and he actually had
a giant stimulus package because of the
global finance oh because of the because
because of our financial crisis but it
was really a global financial crisis so
we had he had close to 100 billion
dollars he was willing to spend on
energy and what's interesting to
remember is that even 10 or 11 years ago
solar and wind weren't really high on
the priority list we talked about
transmission we talked about carbon
capture and storage we talked about
nuclear we talked about a number of
things and the reason was that solar and
wind were still quite expensive in the
last 10 years that has been completely
changed today solar and wind again
without storage low penetration but
solar and wind are in most places in the
u.s. that is reasonably windy places or
reasonably sunny places are actually
much cheaper than any other form of
generation including very very cheap
natural gas which is another big change
in the last decade for the u.s. at least
so so that is incredibly good news we
didn't think that solar and wind was a
viable financial options 10 years ago
today it is in Massachusetts for example
10 years ago we were fighting over a
project called Cape wind which was a big
offshore wind project in Massachusetts
here in Massachusetts it's not very
sunny and it's not very windy on shore
but off shore we have good wind resource
and so the idea was to build windmills
and and they were controversial because
the Kennedys didn't want it to obstruct
their view off of Hyannis Port so there
was lots of local politics and you know
a NIMBYism that is not in my backyard
but in the end one of the big problems
with Cape Wind was that it was about 20
cents a kilowatt hour for the grid to
buy that's wholesale price that's not
selling to us we pay residentially about
21 cents a kilowatt hour in
Massachusetts it's among the highest
price of electricity in the country
maybe a little bit less than Hawaii but
but as high as anywhere else but the
actual wholesale price of electricity is
more like 6 or 7 cents so 20 cents a
kilowatt hour was incredibly high today
offshore wind is less than six cents a
kilowatt hour and
UK and there's actually projects being
planned now for Massachusetts that are
around six cents a kilowatt-hour that's
incredibly exciting in just ten years
nobody would have predicted that kind of
incredible cost draw down for wind and
solar and so in some ways the changes in
prices mean that at least for the next
couple of decades the whole world is
just gonna be building out wind and
solar because it's so cheap and that's
really good news
but understand also that that's just the
first step
decarbonizing our economy involves lots
of different steps
I think another bit of good news is that
electric cars have emerged as a what
looks to be a viable alternative to
gasoline powered vehicles and I think
maybe not in ten years but in 20 years I
suspect that we will see I don't know
twenty to fifty percent of new vehicles
sold in the u.s. being electric least I
hope that we'll get there right now the
price still needs to come down a little
bit but I suspect that will happen the
same way it did for solar and wind
currently electric vehicles are about
twice as expensive as a gasoline powered
equivalent vehicle and there are range
concerns because we don't have enough
charging stations but I suspect over the
next decade or two many places will
solve that problem and the prices will
come down many car companies are
investing in that last year or in 2018
2% of new vehicle sales were electric
vehicles and I think that number will
slowly grow and that's a good thing too
and that's gonna happen all over the
world the bad news is that probably only
gets you thirty to fifty percent of the
way to where you need to go in first of
all that has to be global so you have to
get all the countries in the world to do
it and then there's the really hard
stuff how do you get rid of diesel fuel
for trucks or trains or ships how do you
get rid of heavy industry cement plants
the missions from that smelting how do
you get rid of jet fuel those are really
hard problems and there are a variety of
ideas but they all look very very
expensive
and frankly those are gonna be the hard
parts of decarbonisation and I don't
think we're likely to get started on
those in a very serious way I think
we'll see early experiments and you know
little startups and things but I don't
think we'll have serious market for
those things for several decades into
the future policies gonna have a big
role we need to you know enact policies
that will accelerate this time scale but
from my perspective I think we're
fooling ourselves about how long this
transition is going to take I think if
we're really committed and we had
incredible political will globally it's
gonna take more than 50 years and it
could be closer to 100 I wish that
weren't true I wish we could accelerate
it faster but but the numbers are really
big and really difficult and we also
sometimes forget that it's global you
know in the u.s. we talk about you know
environmental movement talks about
decarbonizing the u.s. as quickly as
possible everybody's focused on when are
we gonna get to zero emissions and from
my perspective people sometimes forget
that getting the u.s. to zero emissions
is actually not the goal the goal is
getting the world to zero emissions the
climate system really doesn't care about
the emissions in the US now that is not
to say us shouldn't play or must I think
envision us must play a leading role I
think we have an obligation as the
world's largest economy and it's the
world's largest carbon emitter per
capita to lead the world towards a
solution but understand the leadership
means getting other people to follow it
doesn't just mean charging ahead and so
our goal should not be to decarbonize
the US as quickly as possible we have a
much more difficult goal which is to
decarbonize the US as quickly as
possible in a manner that makes all of
the other countries of the world want to
follow us and that unfortunately is much
much more challenging because it can't
just be that we do it we have to do it
in a way that looks attractive to others
indeed indeed now with respect to those
concentrated energy sources that you
mentioned jet fuel long-haul diesel at
center it doesn't bio Diesel's
provide a potential entry point there
and also using carbon dioxide at
self at some cost to produce liquid
diesel precursors absolutely so so you
know I teach a course where I make
undergraduates design a low-carbon
economy for the US and it's really
difficult when they actually start to
look at the numbers because
unfortunately what you see is if you
want to use biofuel and biomass can be
turned into diesel fuel or jet fuel
there's a fabulous technology that was
used by the Germans in World War two it
was used by a part tide regime in South
Africa and the 80s called
fischer-tropsch invented bike wonderful
German chemical engineers in the early
nineteen hundreds and you could take
biomass and turn it into very
high-quality jet fuel or diesel fuel
it's fabulous fuel and if you sequester
the co2 it could actually be carbon
negative but and as you say with a
little bit more cost you could scrub co2
out of the air and add hydrogen and
converted to diesel fuel or jet fuel
using similar technology the problem
though is cost that's one problem it's a
lot more expensive so you know today the
global price of oils around 70 bucks but
occasionally it falls to 40 or 50
building a giant fuel plant to may turn
biomass into say biodiesel by the way
the largest biomass refinery in the
world that makes ethanol produces about
12,000 barrels of fuel a day a small
Texas oil refinery is about a hundred
thousand barrels a day so the scale is
just wildly out of sync so part of the
problem is cost so making biodiesel is
much more and much much much more
expensive and scrubbing co2 out of the
air and turning into diesel is probably
a factor of I don't know five to ten
more times more expensive and petroleum
and so right now people aren't willing
to pay that difference but the other
problem is the scale if you start trying
to get all of your fuel from biofuel the
amount of land area required becomes
ridiculous you end up with multiples of
the u.s.
required footprint so just it is gonna
work it's gonna be interesting I think
for diesel trucks things like
potentially hydrogen fuel cell vehicles
it's an interesting idea there's a
company called Nikola motors that's
making trucks I don't think it's likely
to be on your you know interstate
anytime soon but I suspect in certain
places where they could put in the
infrastructure there's a chicken-egg
problem you need to have hydrogen
fueling stations before anybody's gonna
invest in a hydrogen powered truck
because they can't drive a truck if they
can't refill it on the other hand you
can't really pay for making a hydrogen
fueling station if there's no trucks
that want to use it so there's a
chicken-egg problem there I think
there's an interesting opportunity in a
place like California in the i-5
corridor between Sacramento and and Los
Angeles I could imagine putting in you
know three or four hydrogen fueling
stations and requiring that a certain
fraction of trucks use hydrogen to clean
up the pollution in the San Joaquin
Valley I think you might see regional
experiments like that but for now that's
going to be very limited but I think in
the long run hydrogen is gonna give
diesel fuel and diesel trucks have run
for their money but that's gonna take I
think many decades before that happens
and the other alternative though it's
decades long and building infrastructure
it would be electrically powered trains
to replace a fair amount of the long
haul trucking at least I won't get rid
of the short haul but let's get rid of
some of the long haul so you know in the
US you could imagine that the challenge
is that a lot of the long haul transport
you know we used to do it by trains but
the problem is we've torn up most of
those train tracks we've built suburbs
and we've built bicycle paths right
think of all the rail trails that exist
in every community that you know of and
most of the communities don't want to
bring back railroads and it's actually
in a very interesting part of the
climate change dilemma that I think
people don't understand decarbonizing
our economies whether in the US or
anywhere else in the world it's really
the biggest construction project that
humans have ever attempted by far
it is a massive capital investment it's
an ax massive infrastructure investment
and if you want to do it quickly you
can't allow the normal permitting
process to happen truth is that today
it's really difficult to build anything
a transmission line a pipeline a train
track nobody wants it near them nobody
wants the train tracks going next to
their house nobody wants the
transmission line impinging on their
hike or their view or whatever and so as
a result you know NIMBY which is not in
my backyard has become banana which is
build absolutely nothing anywhere near
anything and that's a reality in the US
so what people don't understand is if
you really committed to climate change
you have to suspend kind of community
permitting processes and just have total
control and say okay we're gonna build
this pipeline there we're gonna build
that transmission line there we're gonna
put this train track in here and people
aren't gonna like it so you know it
works in China it's an authoritarian
government it doesn't work so hell in
the US we don't build infrastructure
quickly for good reason people don't
like being forced to to suddenly have
train tracks pop up near their house
think about New York and Boston for
example or New York to DC using 1970s
French technology we should have a train
from Boston to New York that takes about
45 minutes that's the TV that's not the
fancy bullet train you know Chinese or
Japanese stuff this is 40 or 50 year old
technology coming from France the tafa
why don't we have a fast train from New
York to Boston the current train takes a
little under four hours instead of
forty-five minutes it would be great
economically for everybody the reason we
don't is because of Connecticut the only
person who can confiscate homes and
build train tracks straight through from
Boston to New York this government is
the governor of Connecticut and why
would the governor of Connecticut ever
seize people's homes of voters in
Connecticut just so that people can go
from boss
to Boston to New York quicker I don't
think that's ever gonna happen
so I'm I'm kind of skeptical that we're
gonna see in our system of governance
that we're ever gonna see the kind of
infrastructure they that we need to
really fix this problem so I'm skeptical
on trains just because I don't think
we're gonna let it let him be built this
is a little kind of ruddy and humor when
the last general chairman of the
Communist Party in China stepped down
who Jintao I floated the proposal that
the u.s. hire him pay him a billion
dollars a year and give him absolute
authority to build as much
infrastructure as he could get built in
the next ten years yeah you know there's
one part of the u.s. that actually is
really good at building infrastructure
they key they build things quickly and
they do it because they have a totally
different attitude about it exercise and
that's Texas yeah Texas is really good
at it because they just do it they they
don't have nearly the same restrictions
on permit and process and community
permission they just kind of do it and
that's great but it's also I'm sure
there are people who are upset about it
in Texas too so it's complicated it'd be
interesting to see I mean as the
Millennials come online who are clearly
more concerned about climate change than
us old farts or in my case old farts
your case halfway there will be
interested to see are they willing to
make trade-offs about things like having
more trains or having biodiesel plants
nearby etc we will see if they're really
truly sincere about attacking climate
change they may well yield on some of
these things so I'm not as pessimistic
as you are come back you know thirty
years from now it may be that we see a
resurgence of electric trains both light
and heavy but that's a little bit
unknown and as you say it is part of
this collective action problem which is
that kind of the core of making this
even more difficult than it is from a
technology perspective that's right I
mean again if it were just about the
u.s. decarbonizing the u.s. I think you
know people might be willing to kind of
make the sacrifices you know an
inspiring example that some people use
is world war two where we had great
sacrifice and we achieved and build far
more
world war 2 in terms of tanks and
airplanes artillery units and everything
else far more than we expected in a very
short amount of time but people made
real sacrifices we spent 30 percent of
our GDP on the war more than 30 percent
of our GDP for for three and a half
years was an extraordinary sacrifice I
think if it was if we could fix the
problem that way people might be willing
to do that but here's the challenge it's
a global and so the argument well why
would we do that and risk the rest of
the world not following you know if we
don't know that China and India and
Thailand and Myanmar and Pakistan and
you know Indonesia are gonna actually do
the same thing why should we make these
great sacrifices and I think that's the
collective-action part the the
free-rider aspect is really tough to
solve so there's one way to start to
address it that's funny you mentioned
world war two I'm working on an essay
where I'm trying to calculate what the
1944 global GDP equivalent is to fix
climate change 1944 was the peak year of
level of effort in World War two u.s.
was about 50 percent of GDP Germany and
Russia were at 70 percent of GDP Japan
might have been at 80 percent of GDP and
if you do that a global basis I might be
30 percent of global GDP went into
fighting World War two so how many
thirty percent of global GDP does it
take to fix climate and I'm working
those numbers when I'm done with it I'll
publish the result there is one way to
get some traction on this collective
action problem internationally which is
suppose the u.s. the advanced economies
of the eastern rim of Asia and Western
Europe all declared that they were going
to attack this at a world war two level
of intensity and that they were going to
put in place tariffs equal to that cost
from countries that weren't making that
effort hmm so if China and India said
they're not doing anything about climate
then everything that they export to all
these advanced countries will get a very
stiff tariff on them equal to the
imputed capital cost of removing that
much carbon
hmmm interesting yeah that starts the
cycle goin and particularly China and
India are very dependent on exports to
the advanced world so here's a way
without having their agreement we'll
just put up walls and say hey the walls
are comin they start relatively low but
they grow very fast very quickly maybe
we started at $50 a ton carbon
equivalent charge so this idea of
actually what's called you know border
adjustments has actually been around for
a long time people Khanna mists have
been talking about kind of border
adjustments and tariffs for on carbon
for 30 years really since early days of
carbon pricing because they wanted to
make sure that it had an international
component essentially forcing at the
time they were worrying about China but
now they'd be forcing other countries
the problem is that's good for a small
number of rogue countries who refuse to
play ball with the rest of the world for
example if the US and China and you
decided they would do this they could
possibly stick it to Russia or to India
but if say China isn't willing to play
ball frankly I think the India's
dependence on the US or the EU is less
than we think it is right now and they
could be quite sufficient avoiding you
know trade with the EU and the e in the
US and mostly trade with China and
Russia for example and do just fine so I
think trade and and pressure on
countries for climate change is a really
important mechanism and it's certainly
been part of the of the policy
discussions for a very long time but we
understand it before you get there it
needs to be you need to have most of the
countries on board otherwise it just
doesn't work yeah think about that and
play a little game theory there because
one of the interesting things is that
suppose taina didn't want to go along
India then has an interesting
opportunity to grab business from China
and I would say would apply for Myanmar
and Vietnam but anyway let's move along
here let's spend the rest of our time on
geoengineering you spent a lot of time
thinking about it there are
opportunities here there are risks tell
us about your an engineering starting
with what it is and then going through
the risk rewards models preparation what
would should we doing be doing about
geoengineering sure so I think the issue
Engineering first of all it's been a
breath the idea has been around a long
time there was a report from the Johnson
administration in the late 60s on solar
geoengineering is a possible way of
dealing with climate change so again you
know this isn't a new idea it's a very
old idea Edward Teller the physicist
actually I think was a very attracted to
this idea I think that should make
everybody a little reticent knowing
Edward Teller he was the father of the
hydrogen bomb by the way right one of
them well
yeah although people would say Coulomb
might have been actually the father of
the hydrogen bomb but yes he was
certainly one of the father he was
certainly the champion of the hydrogen
bomb if not the father of it maybe the
Godfather of the hydrogen bomb and a
very powerful influence on many
presidents let's explain what it is
Solar geoengineering really is modifying
the albedo of the Earth's atmosphere so
that we could reflect more sunlight to
space essentially so as greenhouse gases
build up in the Earth's atmosphere we
would add more reflective particles to
this to the atmosphere to the
stratosphere and or I guess you could do
with low-level as well and so that we
would reflect more sunlight back to
space essentially putting a Sun Shade on
the earth and cooling the planet to
compensate for climate change now the
first thing to be said is that the
physics of this are not totally
straightforward that is at first glance
reflecting sunlight doesn't cancel out
greenhouse gases you should understand
that the physics of this is different
that is greenhouse gases in the
atmosphere work 24 hours a day whereas
reflecting sunlight only works during
the day when there's actually sunlight
coming in so right away you have a
change in the diurnal cycle that's kind
of important I think most people
understand this from you know if you go
to the desert at night for example as
soon as it gets dark it gets quite cold
in the desert because of clear sky and
the desert radiates heat back to space
whereas if it's cloudy in the desert it
actually stays warm at night and that's
because the clouds add a lot of creative
absorption of
group of infrared radiation and it stays
a lot warmer at night it happens in the
wintertime here in Boston to the very
cold cold nights happen when it's very
clear whereas when it's more stormy you
don't actually get that cold so at first
glance you know they don't actually it
doesn't fix the problem and actually
reflecting sunlight doesn't cancel out
more absorption of infrared radiation
from greenhouse gases what's interesting
is when you put it in a climate model it
works a lot better than you expect it
actually works pretty well it's not
perfect it doesn't perfectly cancel out
the increase in greenhouse gases and
there's some interesting what I call
asymmetric effects for example plants if
you increased carbon dioxide level and
and put reflective particles in the
stratosphere to reflect sunlight to make
it the temperature uniform you could do
that but it turns out plants respond in
interesting ways trees and plants
actually in response to the higher
levels of carbon dioxide they actually
close their stomata the holes in their
leaves and so they actually evaporate
less water and so they actually change
the water cycle substantially in
response to the higher co2 because they
are affected by the higher carbon
dioxide levels as well and so there's
some interesting effects that you have
to be very careful about so it's true
that in general every place is probably
better off if you were to magically
solar Geoengineer the planet as opposed
to just letting carbon dioxide levels
rise but that doesn't mean there aren't
some big changes in some places that's
number one the second thing that's
really important to understand though
and I think this is a good way of
thinking about it this is why Jim I
don't like calling it a techno fix
because it's not a fix I think a good
analogy for it is actually something
more like narcotics morphine for example
you know narcotics can be a very
important pain management medication if
you're having major surgery say you're
having major abdominal surgery for
condition Jim you would want some
painkillers during the surgery right
anesthesia
you know you'll take that morphine any
day because having the surgery without
any anesthesia would be excruciating but
if you only take the anesthesia if you
only take the morphine and never
actually have the surgery that's
probably not a very good strategy either
like morphine solar geoengineering can
be very addicting that is once you start
it you're kind of obliged to keep it
going because if you stop it on a very
short timescale the earth would have
broccoli warm up because now you're
really far from equilibrium and that
would be terrifying so let's just be
clear on what we're talking about we're
talking about a not a techno fix we're
talking about potentially a techno
tourniquet that is going to take away
potentially some of the pain not all of
it but some of the pain but it creates a
variety of new problems and
fundamentally doesn't solve the problem
now there are many people who are
opposed to even thinking about this
issue but the topic of - solar
geoengineering because they say that
it's gonna delay action if people think
there's a techno fix then they won't
feel the pressure to reduce co2
emissions I personally feel that's
really short-sighted I actually think
it's really important to think about
this deeply because again I think the
timescale of climate change is so long
that I think it's gonna be very tempting
for some either consortium of countries
or individual countries to consider
deploying a system of tilt or to
engineering sometime this century I
don't know who's gonna do it I don't
know how it's gonna get done but I feel
like as a scientist as a climate
scientist I have a responsibility to
think very carefully through how it
might be done especially to think about
all the bad ways of doing it and already
I think we've learned something for
example in the 60s through even just a
few years ago
we were talking about sulfur because
that's how volcanoes can cool the
climate when a big volcanic eruption
happens sulfur gets emitted in sulfur
dioxide gets emitted into the
stratosphere and it turns into sulfate
aerosols that reflect sunlight it can
cool the climate a little bit and we've
known this for a long time so you could
think of this as almost artificial
volcanoes people could scatter sulfur
into the stratosphere and it would turn
into sulfate aerosols and cool the
climate the problem is that it might
also affect we think sulfur in this way
might also affect the ozone layer and if
you sustained injections of sulfur for a
long time not just once for from a
volcano but if you actually did this
perennial II for a very long period of
time
you would potentially erode the ozone
layer that protects us from UV radiation
that would be a very bad thing and so
we've learned that really from research
on solar to engineering I think that's
really important example of why it's so
important to think about this it's not
just how to do it it's also how not to
do it because you know some political
leaders somewhere sometime in the next
hundred years I think it's gonna find
this very tempting because it is
relatively inexpensive relative to
changing the energy system of the world
now you know to say that it's not a fix
I think that's really important but I
also think about this the way Churchill
described democracy remember he said
something like you know democracy is the
worst form of government ever invented
except for the alternative and I think
of the same with solar geoengineering
Solar geoengineering is a terrible
arrogant way of fixing a more
fundamental problem in the earth system
and in the human system it's probably a
crazy terrible idea engineering the
climate for every person every living
thing on the planet it's terrifying
and yet it may be better than the
alternative and I think that's that's
important for people to understand that
absolutely what are some of the risks
involved you know because it was just a
magic thing we puts you know I remember
some of the earlier suggestions oh yeah
we had a little sulfur to the diesel
fuel let the Jets just do their thing
but as you point out that's not a good
idea but let's say some of these other
ones that we don't have any known stupid
risks about what are the systemic risks
the complex system risks first of all
doing this in a model is very different
than operationalizing this for the real
world figuring out how to inject
particles into the stratosphere in a
systematic way that safely engineers the
climate for every part of the world
because this particles mix we don't
control them right it's a global what
you're affecting everything you can't
isolate it you can't just do this
for the US so you can't just do this for
China it's much more complicated than
that technically that's a challenge
really doing this in a consistent way
number two the governance problems are
enormous may be insurmountable think
about who gets to control it often when
we talk about this in the u.s. we just
presume them as the current global
superpower that we're in charge but do
you really think that all the countries
of the world are comfortable with
somebody like our current president in
charge of the thermostat for the whole
globe and who gets to decide and by the
way whatever country or group of
countries is in charge of this system
first of all if anything goes wrong
they're gonna get blamed and here's the
other thing if there's a weather-related
disaster whether it was actually caused
by the geoengineering system or not
they're gonna get blamed right that's
true
just like hurricanes are being blamed on
global warming and well global warming
you have some small part about it most
of hurricanes are driven by shorter term
cycles of ocean circulation but people
can't separate those things so you're
gonna get blamed if you actually do
engineer the climate you're gonna have
an awesome responsibility and people are
gonna blame you for everything
so that's kind of daunting and think
about how we would feel if China decided
to do this unilaterally would we really
be comfortable with China having control
over our climate what if there was a big
drought in the u.s. like happened in
2012 major drought 50% of us counties
and emergency drought conditions would
we really be comfortable having China
with they're controlling the knobs
that's I think the answer is no of
course that's part of the problem is
that you know we're tweaking a complex
system with circulations within
circulations within circulation so even
if we do a perfect job of there will be
surprises there will be surprises for
sure yeah and local local effects you
know and it may work right for Argentina
but be a disaster for the Midwest of the
United States or vice versa and yeah and
we already know that to some extent for
example research has shown that if you
globally Geoengineer the climate things
like in for example in Indonesia the
Western warm pool of the Pacific
Indonesia is gonna get drier and so
suppose there were rigorously verifiable
impacts on particular regions or
countries so you knew that Indonesia was
gonna get drier as you did this with the
US have to pay compensation to Indonesia
how would that work
I mean here's what's interesting about
climate change I've been thinking about
this in the context of how humans are
likely to respond to the nature of the
climate challenge and the energy
challenge and and I've got to say I
think the one part that scientists often
underestimate about humans is their
ability to adapt to local challenges
we're incredibly ingeniously
innovative and scrappy when it comes to
fixing problems that affect us that
affect our communities you know when it
comes to long timescales we're terrible
and there's good evolutionary reasons
for that and the same thing with
collective action we're really bad at
global stuff we're tribal you know we
see it in primates oh we see it in
chimpanzees we tend to be tribal we
don't tend to cooperate very well
globally but here's the interesting
thing climate change is a challenge the
likes of which we've never experienced
before and I have a feeling that all of
this is gonna result in a lot of
interesting innovation not necessarily
in energy systems although I hope that
happens also but I am thinking about how
you know if everything I know about
climate change is right it means that
we're gonna experience a lot of climate
change not just in my lifetime
whatever's left of it but my children
and my grandchildren and beyond and that
means that the reality of their impacts
of climate change are gonna Drive
incredible innovation in say in
architecture in agriculture and possibly
even in government you know I actually
think in the same way that you know
World War one led to the idea of a
League of Nations that never really
caught hold World War two then resulted
in the UN
I actually think climate change is gonna
require a new set of global governments
a new form of global governance that we
haven't even imagined yet I don't
exactly know what it's gonna be but when
I think about the issues like solar to
engineering I don't think the UN is up
for the task and I don't think the
framework of the Paris agreement or
anything else like that is really
capable I think something new is going
to emerge and it's not going to emerge
because of altruism or because we all
have some enlightenment I think it's
gonna be because of necessity you know
HG Wells had a great line I think it was
in the time machine where he wrote we
are kept keen on a grindstone of pain
and necessity and I think there's a
truth to that that that a lot of the
innovation in the 21st century is gonna
come not because we're enlightened or we
reach some kind of spiritual connection
with the earth system but because
frankly we're up against it and we have
to innovate or
or fail to survive alright well I think
this has been a very interesting episode
dan I think your closing remarks or a
mixture of optimistic and but that's
reality I think our audience will find
all this very very interesting any final
comments no I think I think I hope you
found it useful I I it's a great topic
it's always a good time good to talk
about it so I hope it's useful
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com